Keeping a Smartsheet program tracker current is usually a manual chore.
Here is a tool that does it for you, from the validated SAS or R you already run on a schedule, with no A-I and no copy and paste.
This is a representative demo of the C-P one-oh-one program tracker.
Click run, and watch a single night's job.
One scheduled run.
The job reads the sheet, computes tonight's operational status, and writes it back to each row by a stable key.
Enrollment drops to At Risk; the database cut moves to Watch and its date slips; the spec ticks up to eighty-five percent; and one genuinely new row is appended, all in a single idempotent upsert.
Look at the log on the right: real reads and writes to the Smartsheet A-P-I, then the status attachment.
And the instant the status cell changed to At Risk, Smartsheet's own workflow, the one a project manager configured once, emailed them.
The code wrote the fact; Smartsheet decided who to tell.
Run the very same job again.
Nothing duplicates, because every row is matched by its key, so it reports rows updated and zero added.
Re-running is always safe; the sheet just converges to the same truthful state.
And the safety boundary is in code, not policy.
When a non-operational column tries to ride along, the ops-only allowlist blocks it and the job stops, so no participant-level data and no reported clinical number can ever reach the cloud.
That is the whole idea.
Your tracker is always current, the alerts are automatic, and you never paste a status again, all from validated SAS and R you already own.
The library ships ready to use: drop in your sheet, your key, and your allowlist, and schedule it.