This is the TRIALMON safety dashboard, on synthetic data.
It is the covering biostatistician's morning view: every participant in the study screened against the pre-specified safety thresholds, with the worst flag surfaced first.
No A-I; deterministic checks only.
Open the hepatic view.
This is the eDISH plane: peak A-L-T against peak bilirubin.
The reference lines are three-times and two-times the upper limit, and the shaded upper-right is the Hy's-Law screening quadrant, where both limbs are elevated together.
Click the participant sitting in that quadrant, and the evidence packet opens: the deterministic backbone first.
The eDISH numbers, the QTcF screen, any adjudicated D-L-T, and the adverse-event counts, each with its own screening flag.
And underneath, the per-visit trajectories, drawn from the as-collected single-draw data: A-L-T and bilirubin climbing visit over visit, QTcF, hemoglobin, neutrophils.
Every value here is a screening flag, never a reported number.
The reported numbers come from the validated tools, Phoenix WinNonlin and Pinnacle 21.
The other views screen the rest of the protocol the same way.
The cardiac view runs QTcF against the I-C-H E-14 thresholds, and the adverse-event view runs the three-plus-three dose-escalation state for each cohort.
That is the whole idea.
The dashboard detects, surfaces, and packages the evidence on a schedule; every clinical decision, causality, seriousness, dose, stays with the medical monitor and the safety review committee.
It detects and pages; the humans decide.