Here's the third companion pipeline — the one you can ship today.
It uses strictly SAS and R, no AI, to keep trial monitoring running while the lead biostatistician is away for a month.
Let me walk through a real month on Study CP-101: how it's set up, what the covering colleague and the manager receive, and what happens when a real safety signal fires — all inside the existing validated environment.
Before leaving, the lead doesn't write new code — they schedule the monitoring programs that already run on demand.
Five jobs: a nightly data refresh with a freshness check, a morning safety scan, a daily digest to the covering colleague, a weekly status pack plus a one-page summary for the manager, and an on-event threshold alert.
It all runs under a service account that outlasts the lead's login.
And a one-page coverage runbook goes to the support and the manager: what green, amber, and red mean, who does what, and the honest note that a flag is a number crossing a line — not an interpretation.
Week one is quiet.
Every morning the covering colleague gets the digest — enrollment, new adverse events, liver and QT flags, the cohort DLT tally, queries — all green.
The most important line is at the bottom: the heartbeat.
It confirms the job ran, on data fresh as of this morning, with no errors.
That's the trick to an unattended month: silence is never assumed.
A missed job or a frozen feed announces itself, instead of hiding behind a green screen.
Week two, an operational signal.
Enrollment slips below its KRI floor — seventy-six percent of plan, with a screen-failure cluster at one site.
The digest renders that row amber.
Notice where it goes: it stays in the routine channel.
The covering colleague reviews it and raises a site action with the project manager — it does not cry wolf at the medical monitor.
And the manager's Friday one-pager simply shows it was flagged and is being handled.
Week three, a real safety signal.
Overnight, a participant in the top dose cohort shows a candidate Hy's-Law lab pattern — ALT over three times the upper limit, and bilirubin over twice it.
This trips the urgent tier, outside the digest, immediately — to the support, a backup, and a role alias, never just one person.
The email carries the medical monitor's number, a thirty-minute acknowledgement requirement, and, crucially, it's honest that this is a screening flag that matches the lab criteria — not a diagnosis.
The medical monitor adjudicates.
And it doesn't just say something happened — it attaches the evidence, already assembled: the eDISH plot with the participant in the Hy's-Law quadrant, the lab trajectory, the dosing timeline, and the exact rule that fired.
On the right is the escalation log, time-stamped automatically: the alert fired at six-oh-seven, was delivered, acknowledged within the SLA, reviewed by the medical monitor — who ordered repeat labs and held dosing — and by Sunday the signal didn't confirm and the cohort was released.
The system did three deterministic things: detected, paged, packaged.
Every clinical decision was the medical monitor's.
Week four, the lead is back.
Waiting for them is a complete, time-stamped archive: every daily log, every digest with its heartbeat, the two notable alerts and how they resolved, the auto-built evidence packet, and a heartbeat history proving every run was accounted for.
Because the whole system is deterministic and validated, there's nothing to reconstruct — no question of what an AI decided and why, no PHI egress to explain.
The loop closed itself: flag, escalate, package, decide, stand down.
The reason a manager can trust this is that it's designed so it can't fail silently.
Four safeguards.
A heartbeat with an independent watcher, so a dead job announces itself.
A data-freshness gate that runs first, so a clean green on stale data — which is worse than red — gets caught.
Alert de-duplication, so one real event alerts once instead of a storm that buries the next signal.
And primary plus backup recipients with an acknowledgement requirement, so a six a.m.
alert never lands in a void.
The rule in the SOP: no news is never interpreted as good news.
So, the bottom line.
This is the lowest-risk of the three pipelines — no AI, no new vendor, no PHI egress, no new validation surface — so there's no approval gate between today and go-live.
It's deterministic and reproducible, so the audit trail is automatic.
It detects, pages, and packages; the humans and the medical monitor still make every call.
And it's necessary, not sufficient: the narrative-triage layer is exactly the seam the AI hybrid fills later.
Ship this now; add AI on top when it's approved.
The peace of mind is simple — monitoring never stops, even silence is verified, and every escalation is automatic and logged, while the lead is unreachable in Europe.